soon after the election there was this
very very strange incident at the annual
meeting of the National Policy Institute
the NPI and that's a very innocuous name
for an organization that many people
believe is sort of you know if not if
not you know white you know National is
very very you know far-right and at its
head at the time was Richard Spencer
he's also the fellow who founded the
alternative right and was a trump
supporter at the time at all and so on
and so on
now what was strange about this meeting
was that at the beginning of it
Spencer was very excited about Trump's
victory so to start the meeting by
addressing the crowd and said hail Trump
now hail are a hero you know hail our
victory we made this happen we dream
Trump into the White House or something
along these lines now that the video
from that meeting that turned up on all
you know all the regular press around
the world and all that but there's a
fella named Harvey Bishop who is a New
Thought blogger now New Thought is named
for a generic kind of philosophy called
mental science positive thinking a
simple way to think of it is that you
know thoughts are causative as I said
earlier somehow what's inside our head
unlike Vegas what's in the mind does
doesn't always stay there what happens
in the mind doesn't always stay there so
New Thought philosophy is that you can
create we create a reality thoughts that
causative we project out into the world
the kind of reality that that we want
was just kind of magic
yep Matt's absolutely is magic and we do
this unconsciously it's magic when you
you know you're doing it and you can you
can kind of do it at will I guess and so
this ship who's you know writes about
new thought all the stuff about we've
made this happen we dream this into
reality that sounded a lot like the kind
of things that people practice mental
science and you thought do Trump himself
is a devotee of New Thought you know
he's a follower of norman vincent peale
author of the power of positive thinking
he went to his sermons when he was a boy
he went there Trump well I say what I
say whether he's using magic but he
certainly is a devotee of positive
thinking positive thinking has its roots
and you thought new thought has its
roots in 19th century occultism and
that's one side of it the other side is
the Chaos magic side which I say in the
book that he probably has never heard of
it but he seems to do it naturally he
seems to have a natural sort of talent
for the ways in which Kaos magicians are
said to operate you know the Soviet
glamour creating chaos moving in and out
of realities adopting truth and
falsehood as just beliefs that you have
temporarily and you dismiss them and you
don't longer do but just the what the
one thing that really sort of sold me on
there being kind of a similar morphology
let's say between New Thought which
generally seems kind of innocuous I mean
Norman Vincent Peale you know he's very
sober you know conservative Reverend and
the Chaos magic tends to be a bit more
wild in punky and and and and dangerous
but they're both results-driven
they're both very specific about it's
not about you know a mystical experience
it's not about you know finding your
higher-self
it's about having some effect in the
real world and and they're very specific
about it and and again it's not just
it's not like expect a miracle it's like
you have to focus on something that's
doable and just needs a little a little
bit more of a nudge and you're saying no
Trump's victory was just the teetered
here and there so if I'm saying if if
you allow for the possibility of in some
way the mind group mind in some way
being to affect things that well just in
chaos theory you know sensitivity to
initial conditions in a little butterfly
flapping over here make something over
there so who knows if nudge of some way
and this is a word that they used in
Paris magic you can even nudge it in a
certain way give it a spin and then it
comes to the the result that you thought
you want but in the long run the idea
was that somehow the people on the
alt-right we had used the Internet as a
way to propagate what-what means you
know Richard Dawkins term for this kind
of cultural
Jeane kind of thing so we that happens
anyway without magic but they were using
one meme in particular which was of this
cartoon character known known as Pepe
the Frog who was a very harmless
amphibian he got drawn into this as I
cut what they called the sigil and the
sigil is a kind of symbol or image that
contains you know magical powers magical
energies the magician's intention of his
will and his imagination and
traditionally you make you know you draw
one you make one you know that kind of
thing but what's called meme magic is an
offshoot of something called chaos magic
and you can understand chaos magic by
thinking of it as something like found
art you know there's traditional art
where the painter paints something and
works on it and the idea that this
becomes a focus for intention yes
exactly I so the Internet becomes this
kind of the realm in which the magic
takes place and long story short what
what people start how this became
something that people were aware of was
that people were posting all this stuff
and they started to see these strange
coincidences between what they were
posting and stuff happening in the real
world and this got coined syncro
mysticism which is a kind of techno
update to Jung's a notion of
synchronicity which is when there's
something something taking place in the
inner world and something in the outer
world and they're absolutely connected
in some indubitable meaningful way but
there's no causal connection you know
there's no there's no way that one or
the other is linked in the usual ways
and that's why we people isn't
meaningful coincidence so this mean
magic rather than have our traditional
imagination inside our heads even have
the internet out there so the Internet
is a kind of externalized imagination
and and makes sense because more and
more regular world is in this kind of
strange interface between its
representation electronically and the
real world and we want more and more
electronic representation of the world
to be more lifelike so everything's HD
everything's
blue-ray whatever it is more and more
stuff like that so again as I said
earlier there's this kind of interchange
going on between reality and its
representation so it makes sense in some
way that stuff happening on the internet
would find it echo out in the world so
that's kind of the theory behind it and
when people notice that this was
happening they said okay what can we
make it happen on purpose I mean you're
not saying that one group of people got
together and did it but it was almost
like self generated yeah I mean there
was some I'm assuming that some people
started it but then when he launched
these things they get picked up out
there and you know there was a basically
I'm not saying every person who did it
was consciously saying you know okay
we're gonna do this but some people were
some people were posting things say hey
look one of the things that happened
they would post things on these sites
and the you're anonymous when you post
them but you get a number there's an 8 8
digit number is assigned to your post
and people kept seeing when they posted
stuff about pepie post itself about
Trump there would be you know duplicates
or triplicates or four of the same
number so it seems some kind of approval
it's somehow you know do more of that
you know and they were betting which
were they going to get a double they're
going to get a trip you know all this
kind of thing so there seems to be some
kind of response you know from from the
medium media that they were using there
was a kind of chaos magic going on
there's a couple of interesting things a
one that the narrowness of Trump's
victory the the condition it was a it
was an incredibly narrow victory it was
almost like if you could see it as a
kind of reverse miracle if you didn't if
you didn't want him to be elected you
could see it was a reverse miracle there
was some kind of inevitability to it
that despite the fact he got three
million less votes he was elected but
also I don't know if you've seen Jordan
Peterson talking about the frog
symbolism and how and how you have I
haven't so he he says this was the most
intense synchronicities he ever he ever
saw as he started becoming aware of what
the frog represented so the Frog the
Frog is between categories so
symbolically it's between categories and
also symbolically the frog was the the
deity of Keck
well that's the other thing all these
strange weird coincidence is the ancient
Egyptian god of heck is a frog and
what's kept the god of chaos and what's
the one word that you would characterize
Trump's you know mo chaos so hey it all
seems to make sense because certainly
within the circle surrounding Trump like
Steve Bannon for example talks about
Judea Savola and yes so there's
certainly an awareness and affinity for
the occult within the we didn't know
well that was the other thing that sent
me thinking like yes it's for the people
watching who's Judas of all in in
February 2017
Steve ban and who was still on Trump's
bench then he gave a speech to what's
known as the human dignity Institute and
this is Khmer DUP of a very conservative
churchmen in the Vatican Bannen was in
LA talked in via Skype but what the New
York Times hit on in this speech which
is peddled the usual global teapot
global tea party a sort of thing in it
was that as you say Bannon named Chuck
Julius Evelyn now if you know who Jesus
Evelyn is you know that he was the 20th
century esoteric thinker who had very
far-right political views he's brilliant
very controversial he was called the
dangerous author by the German novel is
Herman HESA and ever tried to ingratiate
himself first this Mussolini and then
with National Socialists he had he had a
bit of influence on was Mussolini but in
the end he gave up on the Italians and
he gave up on Mussolini because they
weren't fascist enough for him he had
this vision of a kind of absolute
fascism it's kind of theocratic kind of
state and then he tried to get his ideas
across to you know people close to
Hitler but in the long run they they
didn't adopt him and then after the war
he was this kind of fat shadowy figure
in the background the the the kind of
the intellectual provided material about
magic and oh yeah
and he talks precisely about the kind of
using the mind to create reality but I
would say and so he died again like gap
so he died there really so the idea I
mean what was saying is the idea of that
this was consciously created by a
certain number of people is not is not
observed even knowing what we know I
mean it's not absurd it's not
inconceivable I just say that I'm just
sort of saying I'm not saying they did
this I'm saying it looks like all this
is possible and everything is kind of
lined up and well in the long run yes I
do say it's not inconceivable because I
personally accept the reality of
synchronicities I've had too many of
them to dismiss them and a few other
sorts of things and okay if and I would
say my definition of magic is induced
synchronicity they happen can you make
them happen and I could say that's what
the new thought that's what Chaos magic
choice to do so that to me is the is the
crux not that they happen they do happen
can you make them happen but nobody ever
loved
as I said in up until his death in the
70s after World War two he was this kind
of intellectual figure you know doing
the philosophy for a variety of
different far-right groups that were
rising up out of the rubble but in the
20s he contributed a series of articles
to esoteric journal and they're all
about being able to focus the mind
intently on your goal and and he talks
about the absolute individual and again
it's this idea that some fundamental
level of our being you know before you
are you your personality and you know
you do what you do you live where you
live in some very very basic bedrock
level of being you know it's the general
mystical idea that was somehow we are
the ultimate reality already you know we
don't know what we've forgotten it but
if you can get down to that level then
you can narrow and focus your intent
enough to be able to affect reality at
the time in the 20s whenever lo was
doing this and he was doing rituals and
and different
practices what he wanted to do the
reality he wanted to affect was
Mussolini's fascist he wanted to so to
imbue them with the ancient Roman
virtues and I don't know how successful
he was but this is what he was trying to
do so even then you have EV Allah who it
was informing Steve Manon he's also a
big name for all the old right people
he's one of the top kind of intellectual
figures that they name check to show
that they're more sophisticated than the
earlier kind of skinheads and Evelyn is
also top of the reading list for this
fellow named Alexander Dugan who in
different ways he has yeah well he's
again depending who you're talking to
oh no don't know Putin never heard of me
oh yes I saw him the other day you know
you know at different times Dugan
himself as has said contrary things
about because how much influence our
contact he's had but again if you know
what Dugan is interested in and he's
interested in some very odd things and
if you follow Putin speeches and
actually what he's done in the world you
can see where if not everything
certainly some areas where Duggan's
ideas have which again go back to people
like Evelyn and chaos magic and a
variety of different fascist
totalitarian kind of ideas he does this
kind of Lego game with ideologies where
he takes he takes the good bits that say
from national socialism or fascism
stallin ISM and and puts them together
and there's something equals the fourth
political theory which he's working on
creating it hasn't arrived yet but it's
something that's a work in progress but
it's something to replace the global you
know liberal liberalism that's come upon
us and Francis Fukuyama pointed to his
showing the end of history back in the
early nineties I mean that that that
vision nauseates do again and you know
it doesn't go down that well with Putin
either because he's talking about kind
of return to blood and soil for that my
guess is it I'm sorry it's more of a
return to like blood and soil yes yeah
well I mean yeah yeah well it's the
whole I guess it's a whole idea it's
it's nationalistic but it's the whole
well the idea that the end of history
arrived when you know free market values
and liberal democracy have spread around
the whole
I mean for some people yes clap hands
other people like Dugan and others say
so this is no they so this is the world
being just turned into a market place
you know for them you know the
globalization for them is basically
meaning that you know wherever the US or
the Western the Western powers go and
liberate people it's basically to open
up a new market and you know we have to
say you know there's a lot to be said
for that at that point of view but his
alternative to that is this kind of
theocratic he talks about having seeing
a fascist state from Vladivostok to
Dublin and he talks about somebody
called Eurasia and Eurasia is the idea
that Russia is not a backward cousin of
Europe who's never quite catching up to
European Western ways it's a completely
new civilization of its own as different
routes different influences different
aims different values and he talks about
rather than this linear idea of history
of being you know there's a beginning
and you know it's just cumulative it's
more like there's individual cultures it
goes back to a German historian and
oswald spengler they wrote a book called
the decline of the West incidentally but
he talked about rather than
civilizations or history being this
linear thing with one civilization
growing on top of the other were they're
all self-enclosed
and they have their own value so that
there's not one mathematics there's you
know Persian mathematics and there's the
it talks about these doofus Faustian
culture any case that's the idea and
again that's very much along the lines
not only in the right not only sort of
thing do again century but also in the
left the whole idea that you know oh
there isn't one oppressive truth you
know there's lots of different truths
anything goes you know and it's all
socially constructed well that's just
trickled down
Spengler miss pang was saying no there
isn't one civilizations are like flowers
they're in the same garden but they're
not the same flower and they're not all
working to get to one big flower at the
end each one grows matures blooms and
dies what impact did it have on you or
how exciting was it to to discover that
this this stuff that you've been
interested in for so long was suddenly
showing up in all of these crazy ways
facilitated by the Internet as this kind
of you know I've thought for a while the
Internet is kind of a it's it's by
democratizing information it's kind of a
allowing all of this stuff to bubble up
from the from the cracks in our culture
and in a way that would make perfect
sense why magic the occult positive
thinking is now coming up and is is
changing politics and changing culture
at the surface of the highest levels
well I
it's it's excited I woke up when I woke
up when I saw that the New York Times
had had name-check Julia Zavala I
thought well you know things have
changed now in the New York Times first
place to mention Julie said oh there was
something but then for them to mention
it in the context of at the time someone
who was a close advisor to Trump giving
a talk to people who Vatican and then
even within that the context where he
refers to ever law is in reference to
Putin and in reference to this fellow
Dugan who's around Putin noticed oh wow
you know all the stuff that's on the
fringe and on the margins as to the
center and that again confirmed for me
the idea that reality had changed
something had changed again it's not we
still have three dimensions you know the
still the past present future but how do
we understand these things how we
understand what it means to be human I
wouldn't stand freedom all these you
know they're very important things how
we even communicate it's very difficult
to talk about things I mean I'm one of
the things in this article I wrote about
Peterson was that and I say it in the
book is that you had this strange thing
happening where you know liberal left
students were shouting down professors
or people giving a talk or lecture and
they were saying things you know they
didn't like okay you can disagree that's
fine but what is the difference between
you shouting professors down now and
Nazi youth shouting down Jewish
professors and you know in the 30s
because you know yes by all means
students in protests but all student
protests aren't about sweetness and
light you know
and and you know God you know if you go
back even earlier you know
the university students in Germany in
the 19th century were incredibly
nationalists and so their protests were
all about nationalism they were burning
foreign books and things like that so it
struck me as I said we're just it's
exciting but then the same time I don't
know if people are prepared to actually
understand what it means I mean I I
worked really hard at trying to
communicate these esoteric hermetic
ideas in a language in the context that
you don't have to agree with them but at
least they make sense and I can show
that they're not that far away from any
concerns of the mainstream edition is it
exciting or terrifying well it's it's
the thing that's both you know it's a
you're sort of on the edge and there's
no guarantee where it's going to go and
that's what all these people say it's up
to you it's not an automatic process it
isn't the class war you know like oh the
the march of history we'll just if you
just let history do itself it'll take
it'll take the line of least resistance
so if you don't like what's happening
will you have to use magic yourself to
kind of try and change it I think at all
times it's very good to be aware of
what's going on inside your head I think
that's that's the key and if you don't
have things going on there then other
things will be will be in there okay so
I said what happens in the mind doesn't
know necessarily always stay there but
it might what happens in somebody else's
mind what might wind up inside yours too
so the whole idea of wakefulness
attention all these things which have a
kind of cliche but an all character to
them that but they're actually you know
they're real and again it doesn't mean
you know shouting down Trump or doing
anti-trump stuff or something it just
means being very very aware in a way
because I think in these times when it's
very it's it is sensitivity to initial
conditions a little thing can and can
make something happen so are we back in
the time of Magic III I don't think we
ever left it I think it's more out in
the open now and as I say we're not
really prepared to how as you say we can
dismiss it we can say oh those guys that
you know doing these whatever it is and
be critical about it but we're not
really prepared how to deal with it
positively and I don't mean in the sense
of everybody going out and
you know sorry casting spells or reading
tarot cards in the sense of accepting
but what does it mean if it's not if it
isn't just all this superstition
everyone's told us I mean one of the
things I I like to think of it as there
was the time we couldn't talk about sex
without it you just couldn't talk about
it or you couldn't talk it without it
being much notes wink wink you know
slightly titillating you know kind of
thing but now we can talk about if you
talk about God and all different kinds
of ways very clinically very frank and
straightforward and it makes it
absolutely uninteresting in many ways
but we still can't talk about the occult
or magic in that way you still get the
x-files you know soundtrack comes on in
the background and the blue feeling
comes up and don't want to lose that
entirely just like you don't want to
lose you know the allure of sex but you
also want to be able to talk about the
open to open it up you know to make it
to make as low so yeah otherwise you're
a victim and people who are are the
people going to do it you know if if
you're not if reality's up for grabs
then get your skates on because if
you're not gonna do it then other people
going to and you'll be stuck with the
reality that's there and again I don't
mean sitting at home and you know
visualizing reality just just being
aware that these things work
consciousness is something that's it
doesn't just it's not just there it's
not like ring-fenced and protect it it's
it's part of a continuum of other things
and things can get in without you even
consciously knowing it I mean they this
is one of the things gaps were felt when
in Germany in the 20s because he was
around some of the early Nazi rallies
and he said and this is why he talks
about that those group rallies precisely
as the expression of the magical
structure of consciousness and one of
the one of the characteristics of that
is this kind of continuum a visceral
continuum it's not rational it operates
below below the rational line and he
talks about how when he went to these
rallies even though he resisted it he
could feel you could feel the kind of
energy whatever you want to call it
coming into him and not only ocultist
but people in you know science people
like Rupert Sheldrake and people like
that they talk about something let's
along those lines so I think these
things are true I think we just need to
be we need to stay awake basically